Har-ma Press records LSC.2181
UCLA Library Special Collections
Har-ma Press Records
1979-1984
LSC.2181
UCLA Library Special Collections
0.2 linear feet (1 box)
Correspondence between Muir Dawson, Harold Smith, and Roger Levenson, and other documents regarding the development, manufacture and sale of the Har-ma printing press.
Har-Ma Press.
Restrictions on Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. Advance notice required for access. Contact the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk for paging information.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 7816482
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Purchase, 2013.
Biography/History
The Har-ma Press was invented in the late 1970s by Harold Smith, an engineer from Sacramento, California. The name of the press is derived from the first three letters of Harold Smith's first name and the last two letters of his wife, Alma's first name. Harold and Alma Smith worked closely as authors and printers.
In 1978, the Har-ma caught the eye of Roger Levenson, printer and proprietor of Tamalpais Press, during a demonstration by Smith at a printer's fair. Levenson immediately ordered one for himself, and Smith subsequently consulted Levenson on design improvements as he built additional presses. Levenson also recommended the Har-ma to Muir Dawson, owner and operator of Dawson's Bookshop in Los Angeles. Dawson purchased a Har-ma press for the bookshop, and arranged the sale of several others, including one to UCLA. Smith built a total of 15 presses: a prototype numbered 0 and numbers 1-16, but no number 13. Harold Smith died in 1999.
Scope and Content
Materials documenting the development of the Har-ma printing press, invented by Harold Smith. Includes sales information, correspondence documenting bookseller Muir Dawson's relationship with Harold Smith during the years Smith built the presses, operating instructions, a list of the locations of each press, and two artists' books produced on a Har-ma press.
Arrangement note
Collection arranged by subject.
Dawson, Muir; Levenson, Roger, 1914-1994; Smith, Harold; Hand presses; Printing presses
- Correspondence between Muir Dawson and Roger Levenson, 1979-1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  9 letters and 4 postcards exchanged between Muir Dawson and Roger Levenson about the Har-ma Press.
- Correspondence between Muir Dawson and Harold Smith, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  5 Letters exchanged between Muir Dawson and Harold Smith regarding acquisitions of presses for various clients. Also included is one handwritten thank you note from Smith to Dawson as well as another handwritten note from Harold and Alma Smith to the Dawsons.
- Correspondence between Muir Dawson and Jean P. Whyte, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  13 Letters exchanged between Muir Dawson and Jean P. Whyte, a professor from Monash University in Victoria, Australia, regarding the sale of Har-ma Press #11 to Monash University.
- Correspondences regarding interest in Har-ma Press., 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  7 letters between multiple individuals. The bulk of the letters demonstrate interest by different people in acquiring a Har-ma Press. A couple of letters concern the sale of Har-Ma Press #8 to UCLA professor of Spanish, Enrique Cepeda.
- Annotated Letter about missing press # 13., 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  This letter between Roger Levenson and an unknown correspondent documents the locations of all 15 Har-ma presses that Smith built. The letter also contains a notation in Muir Dawson's hand about the missing press # 13 that reads as follows: "9/23/84 Roger says Harold tells him there is no # 13."
- Messages in Wood, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  A book of text and images written and drawn by the Smiths and produced by Harold and Alma on a Har-ma Press.
- The Har-ma Press, 1981; Pamphlet. 5 5/8 x 3 3/4 inches, (14) pp. Illustrated. Green printed wrappers, stitched, with a blind-stamped image of a Har-Ma press on the front cover. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Limited edition of 150 copies printed on Har-ma Press number 8 (UCLA Horn Press) as a keepsake for the members of the Rounce and Coffin Club.
- Publicity, 1978-1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Includes drafts of two articles written by Muir Dawson and Roger Levenson in the UCLA Librarian and Fine Print Magazine, with original artwork for the latter. There are 7 copies of the article in the UCLA Librarian. Also included is a letterhead with a photograph of a Har-ma Press for sale purposes in the Printer’s Fair, Marin County, 11/5/78. Four photocopies of this letterhead are included.
- Har-ma Press Sales, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Original purchase order and shipping manifest of Har-ma Press #11 to Monash University. There are two copies of the shipping manifest. Also included is a shipping manifest from California Motor Express regarding the sale of books from Dawson’s bookshop to the Book Club of California and a business card from Staudt International Service Corp, an international freight company. Shipping manifests for presses delivered to Dawson’s book shop and original billing for the sale of two presses is also a part of this file.
- Har-ma Press operating instructions, Unknown (Box 1, Folder 10)
  A set of printed instructions and a separate set of typed instructions on how to operate the Har-ma Press. There are also 3 handwritten notes on disassembling the press for moving or other operations tips based on experience with working with the press.
- Program Announcements, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Program announcements for “An Evening devoted to the Past, Present and Future of Handpresses,” February 5, 1981 at Dawson’s Book Shop featuring Harold and Alma Smith and Roger Levenson.